Guide to the Henry Charlton Bastian papers, 1841-1932 and undated, bulk 1870-1920
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henry Charlton Bastian papers 1841-1932 and undated bulk 1870-1920
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bastian, H. Charlton.
2.0 linear feet Extent: Approx. 1200 Items
Prominent British scientist active in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, known for his work on spontaneous generation (abiogenesis) and neurological science. Collection dates from 1841-1932 and documents Bastian's rise as a neuroscientist, biologist, writer, and researcher, and encompasses typed and manuscript correspondence, research notes, offprints, handwritten drafts, early scientific photographs, pencil and ink drawings, and professional reviews and accolades. The largest series contains correspondence dating from 1856 to 1932, from prominent scientists, neurologists, scholars, publishers, assistants, and friends, including Louis Pasteur, Caleb Saleeby, Thomas Huxley, Sir John Bretland Farmer, Aristide Pratelle, William Paton Ker; there are also letters written by Bastian, including exchanges with the Académie des Sciences in France. The materials chiefly concern Bastian's early 20th century work on abiogenesis, but also on aphasia and paralysis. The collection also contains numerous pieces of correspondence addressed to Bastian's daughter, Sybil Bastian, who was also a scientist, and his wife Julia. Other materials include obituaries, condolence letters, Christmas cards, and newspaper clippings. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
RL.00088
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Henry Charlton Bastian papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2012.
Biographical Note
Henry Charlton Bastian (1937-1915), born in Truro, Cornwall, was a pioneer in the field of neurology. He studied at University College, London and was elected a fellow of the Royal Society of London. Bastian was known for his works on aphasia, the loss of the ability to express or understand speech due to brain damage. He also demonstrated Bastian's Law, which holds that the complete section of the upper spinal cord abolishes reflexes and muscular tone below the level of the lesion. He published various works on paralysis and coined the term kinesthesia to describe the sense of body motion. Bastian was also known for his work on abiogenesis, less accurately known as spontaneous generation. Bastian, in sharp contrast to Pasteur, Koch, Huxley and Darwin, controversially argued that there was no fixed boundary between living and nonliving organic matter and that the processes that generated life in an earlier stage could still be operating in the present. His experiments, however, could not be reproduced, and his views were generally discredited in the profession.
Collection Overview
The Henry Charlton Bastian collection dates from 1841 to 1932, with the bulk of the materials falling between 1870 and 1920. The papers document Bastian's rise as a neurologist, writer, and researcher, and encompass typed and manuscript correspondence, research notes, offprints, articles, handwritten drafts, early scientific photographs, pencil and ink drawings, and professional reviews and accolades.
The bulk of the collection is made up of correspondence dating from 1856-1932, chiefly from prominent scientists, neurologists, scholars, publishers, assistants, and friends--including Louis Pasteur, Caleb Saleeby, Thomas Huxley and his wife Annie, Sir John Bretland Farmer, Aristide Pratelle, and William Paton Ker, among many others. There is a group of testimonial letters from fellow scientists. There are a number of outgoing pieces as well written by Bastian which include exchanges with the Académie des sciences of France. The correspondence as well as the research notes and writings chiefly concern Bastian's work on abiogenesis, but also his neurological research on aphasia and paralysis. The collection also contains numerous pieces of correspondence addressed to Bastian's daughter, Sybil Bastian, who was also a scientist, and Bastian's wife Julia; there are in particular many condolence letters received following Bastian's death in 1915. The professional papers include Bastian's research drawings and early photomicrographs, reviews of his work, reprints, and diplomas. Other materials are more personal, and include obituaries, Christmas cards, and a newspaper clipping reporting the details of London's 1919 victory march.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged in the following series: Correspondence, Personal Papers, and Professional Papers. Within series, items are arranged in chronological order, with undated items placed at the end of their respective series and arranged alphabetically by author or title.
Subject Headings
Académie des sciences (France); Bastian, H. Charlton, 1837-1915; Bastian, Julia; Bastian, Sybil; Farmer, John Bretland, 1865-1944; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895; Ker, William Paton, 1855-1923; Pasteur, Louis, 1822-1895; Pratelle, Aristide; Saleeby, Caleb Williams, 1878-1940; Aphasia; Life -- Origin; Muscular sense; Neurology -- History; Paralysis; Photomicrography; Scientists -- England -- Correspondence; Spontaneous generation; Drawings; Photomicrographs; History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1856-1932 and undated, bulk 1870-1920, (3 boxes)
  Correspondence, arranged chronologically, between Bastian and various notable scientists, scholars and doctors, such as Sir John Bretland Farmer, Thomas Huxley and his wife Annie, Louis Pasteur, William Paton Ker, Caleb Saleeby, Hector Grasset, William Pennington Cocks, and assistants Albert and Alexandre Mary. There is also a group of exchanges between Bastian and the Académie des Sciences of France. The majority of the correspondence is written to Bastian, but there are some drafts penned by Bastian. The correspondence frequently concerns Bastian's controversial work on abiogenesis. Also includes exchanges between Bastian and publishing companies, concerning translations of his numerous works; a series of letters appears from well-known publisher Félix Alcan from Metz. Bastian's wife, Julia, and daughter, Sybil also figure as recipients and writers of correspondence, with many condolence letters received after Bastian's death. Undated letters are placed at the end of the series and arranged alphabetically. Of interest among these is a manuscript document written after Bastian's death by his assistants, Albert and Alexandre verifying Bastian's experiments on the origin of life.
  - Cocks, William Pennington: Autograph holiday greetings letter with self-portrait in ink. 1 page, 1856 Dec. 24 (Box 1)
  - Cocks, William Pennington: Autograph holiday greetings letter with ink sketch of 2 skeletons holding a punch bowl. 1 page, 1862 Dec. 24 (Box 1)
  - Cocks, William Pennington: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1864 Dec. 4 (Box 1)
  - Cocks, William Pennington: Autograph holiday greetings letter with ink sketch. 1 page, 1866 Dec. 24 (Box 1)
  - Sieveking, E. H.: Autograph letter signed (testimonial letter on Bastian's behalf). 2 pp., 1867 Nov. 6 (Box 1)
  - Sibson, Francis: Autograph letter signed (testimonial on Bastian's behalf). 4 pp., 1867 Nov. 6 (Box 1)
  - Jones, C. Handfield: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 3 pp., 1867 Nov. 21 (Box 1)
  - Rawlings, A. S.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, appointing him as assistant physician to National Hospital for the Paralysed and Insane. 2 pp., 1868 Jan. 18 (Box 1)
  - Lawton(?), Henry: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1869 Nov. 14 (Box 1)
  - N[--], R. Autograph letter signed to Bastian congratulating him on his marriage. 1 page, 1869 (Box 1)
  - Beale, Lionel S.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, mentioning "Tyndall's outrageous letter." 3 pp., 1870 Apr. 13 (Box 1)
  - Bennett, Alfred W.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian concerning bacteriology. 2 pp., 1870 Oct. 21 (Box 1)
  - Frankland, Edward: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 4 pp., 1870 Nov. 6 (Box 1)
  - Rolleston, George: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1870 (Box 1)
  - Sisson, R. S.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, mentioning spontaneous generation. 3 pp., 1872 Nov. 22 (Box 1)
  - Roberts, William: Autograph letter signed to Bastian describing bacteriological experiments. 8 pp., 1873 Mar. 14 (Box 1)
  - Cocks, William Pennington: Autograph letter signed to Bastian discussing science. 3 pp., 1873 May 3 (Box 1)
  - Mivart, St. George: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, mentioning Huxley's "arrogant preface" to Huxley's Critiques and Essays. 4 pp., 1873 May 9 (Box 1)
  - Agnew, J. W.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, enclosing a cutting of William Valentine's letter to the editor of the Argus on spontaneous generation. 3+ pp., 1875 Mar. 19 (Box 1)
  - Mackintosh, Angus: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, mentioning Pasteur and Tyndall. 3 pp., 1876 Aug. 21 (Box 1)
  - Pasteur: Typed transcript of Pasteur's letter to the Lancet published on Mar. 3, 1877, disputing a claim by Bastian concerning abiogenesis, 1877 Mar. 3 (Box 1)
  - Tarnover(?), E. L. Letter signed to Bastian discussing publication of some of his works. 6 pp., 1877 Apr. 17 (Box 1)
  - Bastian: Group of correspondence etc. between Bastian and the Académie des Sciences. 12 pieces. Includes references to Pasteur. 1877 Feb.-July (Box 1)
  - Lombard, J. S.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, mentioning the controversy between Bastian and Tyndall. 3 pp., 1878 Feb. 15 (Box 1)
  - Lombard, J. S. Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 4 pp., 1879 Jan. 10 (Box 1)
  - Macmillan, Frederick: Autograph letter signed to Bastian regarding costs for Beginnings of Life and Paralysis. 3 pp., 1879 Mar. 6 (Box 1)
  - Bastian (?): Portion of autograph letter to Mr. Macmillan, mentioning Bastian's Beginnings of Life. 2 pp., 1879 Mar. 14 (Box 1)
  - Kegan, Paul; F. Alcan, Bastian: Correspondence regarding sales of the French edition of Bastian's The Brain as an Organ of Mind. 9 pieces, 1887-1893 (Box 1)
  - Bastian; Kegan, Paul: Correspondence regarding setting the price for a reprint of Bastian's The Brain as an Organ of Mind. 6 pieces., 1880-1883 (Box 1)
  - Bastian; Kegan, Paul: Correspondence regarding royalties for Bastian's The Brain as an Organ of Mind. 3 pieces. Includes an autograph document by Bastian, 1880 Feb. 13 (Box 1)
  - Walshe, W. H.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 3+ pp., 1880 June 1 (Box 1)
  - Lombard, J. S.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian mentioning Brown-Sequard. 4 pp., 1880 June 5 (Box 1)
  - Marshall, John: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1 page, 1880 June 7 (Box 1)
  - C. Kegan Paul & Co.: Typed letter signed concerning French royalties for The Brain as an Organ of Mind. Annotated by Bastian. 2 pp., 1880 July 19 (Box 1)
  - Henderson, George C.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, with cover. 2 pp., 1880 Dec. 2 (Box 1)
  - Germer Baillière: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, with Bastian's pencil note. 1 page, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Reale Accademia di Medicina di Torino: Manuscript document in Italian addressed to Bastian. 1 page, 1883 Feb. 12 (Box 1)
  - Huxley, Thomas: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2+ pp., 1883 July 8 (Box 1)
  - Orange, Dr. W.: 2 autograph letters signed to Bastian. Dr. Orange was associated with the Broadmoor Criminal Lunatic Asylum. 7 pp., 1884 Feb. 10 (Box 1)
  - Cuffe, H.: Letter signed concerned Bastian's serving as an expert witness in murder cases. 2 pp., 1884 Feb. 18 (Box 1)
  - Huguenet, P. (for F. Alcan): Autograph letter signed to Bastian regarding publishing matters. 2 pp., 1884 Feb. 22 (Box 1)
  - Collins, William Job: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1+ page, 1884 July 30 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Eustace: Autograph letter signed to Bastian thanking him for copy of Aphasia. 3 pp., 1886 Jan. 28 (Box 1)
  - Carr, J. Walker: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2+ pp., 1886 Feb. 17 (Box 1)
  - Austin, Ben. W.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian from the secretary of the Northwestern Literary and Historical Society of Sioux City, IA. 1 page, 1886 Mar. 29 (Box 1)
  - Cuffe, H. Autograph letter signed to Bastian, with cover. 2 pp., 1886 June 24 (Box 1)
  - Richet, Charles: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1 sheet., 1886 July 2 (Box 1)
  - Somes(?), W.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian thanking him for copy of Paralyses. 1 page, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Walshe, W. H: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1886 Aug. 1 (Box 1)
  - Barlow, Thomas: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1886 Aug. 3 (Box 1)
  - Poore. G. W.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1 page, 1886 Aug. 3 (Box 1)
  - Roberts, J[--]: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1886 Aug. 4 (Box 1)
  - Swain, R. Autograph letter signed to Bastian thanking him for copy of Paralyses. 2 pp., 1886 Aug. 4 (Box 1)
  - Pye-Smith, P. H.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1886 Sept. 24 (Box 1)
  - [---]: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2+ pp., 1886 Nov. 11 (Box 1)
  - Bastian; Macmillan: Correspondence concerning Paralysis from Brain Disease and The Beginnings of Life. 8 pieces plus envelope, 1893-1894 (Box 1)
  - Pasmore, Edwin: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1+ page, 1890 Jan. 7 (Box 1)
  - Clark, Andrew; Richard Quain, Edward Sieveking: Testimonial letters in favor of Bastian. Cover sheet plus 3 autograph letters signed, 1890 (Box 1)
  - Steward, Thomas Grainger: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1 page, 1893 Jan. 30 (Box 1)
  - Nixon, C. J.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1893 Jan. 25 (Box 1)
  - Philipson, George Hare: Autograph letter signed to Bastian thanking him for copy of Hysterical & Functional Paralysis. 3 pp., 1893 Jan. 28 (Box 1)
  - Gulland, George Lovell: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, with cover. 3 pp., 1893 Feb. 8 (Box 1)
  - Lewis, H. K.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian concerning a second edition of Hysterical Paralysis. 2 pp., 1893 Feb. 8 (Box 1)
  - Lewis, H. K.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian giving costs for second edition of Hysterical Paralysis. 1 page, 1893 Feb. 15 (Box 1)
  - Dougall, John: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 4 pp., 1893 (Box 1)
  - Hosford, John Stroud: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 4 pp., 1895 Sept. 16 (Box 1)
  - Hosford, John Stroud: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, discussing abiogenesis. 4 pp., 1895 Sept. 22 (Box 1)
  - Hosford, John Stroud: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, mentioning abiogenesis. 2 pp., 1895 Sept. 25 (Box 1)
  - Bolton, J. S.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, with cover. 2 pp., 1895 Oct. 4 (Box 1)
  - De Buck, D. D.: Autograph postcard signed to Bastian, 1898 Jan. 13 (Box 1)
  - Leicester, J. C. Holdich: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, with cover. 2 pp., 1898 Feb. 15 (Box 1)
  - D. Appleton & Co.: Autograph letter to Bastian. 2 pp., 1898 Feb. 24 (Box 1)
  - Russell, J. S. R.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, thanking him for a copy of Aphasia. 2 pp., 1898 May 2 (Box 1)
  - Wyllie, John: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, with cover, thanking him for a copy of Aphasia. 1 page, 1898 May 4 (Box 1)
  - Poore, G. V.: Autograph note signed to Bastian. 12 pp., 1898 May 5 (Box 1)
  - [---], Ch.: Autograph letter in French concerning Bastian's book on aphasia. 1 p., 1898 May 10 (Box 1)
  - Gulland, G. Lovell: Autograph letter signed thanking him for copy of Aphasia. 2 pp., 1898 May 15 (Box 1)
  - Reale Accademia di Medicina di Torino: Printed announcement of the death of Prof. Carlo Giacomini, addressed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1898 July 5 (Box 1)
  - Horsburgh, J. M.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian appointing him consulting physician to the University College Hospital. 1 page, 1898 Aug. 3 (Box 1)
  - Jackson, J. Hughlings: Autograph letter signed to Sybil Bastian thanking her for 2 photographs. 1 page, 1898 Sept. 17 (Box 1)
  - Societá Medico-Chirurgica di Bologna: Manuscript notice appointing Bastian a foreign corresponding member. 1 page, 1900 Mar. 8 (Box 1)
  - Broadbent, William: Autograph letter signed to Bastian thanking him for "your book on the Brain." 2+ pp., 1900 June 5 (Box 1)
  - Unione Tip.-Editrice Torinese: Autograph letter signed from L. Moriondo(?). 2 pp., 1901 Nov. 21 (Box 1)
  - John Bale Sons & Danielsson: Invoice for preparing "tone blocks," with cover. 1 page, 1901 Dec. 6 (Box 1)
  - John Bale Sons & Danielsson: Typed letter concerning cost of illustrations. 1 page, 1901 Dec. 24 (Box 1)
  - Bastian: Autograph draft of letter to John Bale Sons & Danielsson regarding cost of blocks for Heterogenesis, 1901 (Box 1)
  - Wright, Jonathan: Autograph postcard signed to Bastian, 1901 (Box 1)
  - John Bale Sons & Danielsson: Typed letter concerning cost of illustrations, 1902 Jan. 6 (Box 1)
  - R. Accademia dei Lincei: Typed letter signed to Bastian, in Italian. 1+ page plus cover and separate sheet with partial English translation of the letter, 1902 Apr. 4 (Box 1)
  - Bastian: Autograph letter signed (draft) to Michael Foster. 2 pp., 1902 Apr. 7 (Box 1)
  - Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin: Correspondence with Bastian concerning Bastian's paper on the eggs of Hydatina senta. 2 pieces. 3 pp., 1902 Apr. 15 (Box 1)
  - Foster, Michael: Typed letter signed to Bastian concerning Bastian's Note on the transformation...of the entire contents of the egg of Hydatina senta into a large ciliate belonging to the genus Otostoma. 1 page, 1902 Apr. 17 (Box 1)
  - Fry, Edward: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1902 July 5 (Box 1)
  - Pavy, F. W.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1+ page, 1902 July 8 (Box 1)
  - Hudson, C. J.: 2 autograph letters signed to Bastian discussing Bastian's abiogenesis work. 7 pp., 1902 July 10 (Box 1)
  - Basel(?), Alfred: autograph letter to Toynbee(?) 2 pp., 1902 Nov. 15 (Box 1)
  - Larmor, Joseph: Autograph letter signed to Bastian rejecting Bastian's On the relations between certain diatoms and the fission products of a parasitic alga with Bastian's reply. 2+ pp., 1903 Jan. 26 (Box 1)
  - Worden(?), J. W.: Autograph letter to Miss Masson(?) 2 pp., 1903 Feb. 9 (Box 1)
  - Larmor, Joseph: Autograph letter signed to Bastian regarding Bastian's On the relations between certain diatoms and the fission products of a parasitic alga, with cover. 2 pp., 1903 Feb. 10 (Box 1)
  - Farmer, John Bretland: Autograph letter signed to Bastian regarding Bastian's On the relations between certain diatoms and the fission products of a parasitic alga. 2+ pp., 1903 Apr. 2 (Box 1)
  - Avebury, Lord (John Lubbock): Autograph postcard signed to Bastian thanking him for sending a copy of Studies in Heterogenesis, 1903 July 5 (Box 1)
  - [---], Mary: Autographed letter to Miss Eustace Smith inviting her to tea. 1 pp., 1903 July 6 (Box 1)
  - Fry, Edward: Autograph postcard signed to Bastian, 1903 July 20 (Box 1)
  - Avebury, Lord (John Lubbock): Autograph postcard signed to Bastian thanking him for sending a copy of Studies in Heterogenesis, 1903 July 28 (Box 1)
  - John Bale Sons & Danielsson: Invoices for printing costs of Bastian's Heterogenesis.3 ff., 1903 Sept. 30 and Nov. 24 (Box 1)
  - Mitchell, T. W.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, with cover, discussing aphasia. 3+ pp., 1904 Apr. 11 (Box 1)
  - Macfie, Ronald Campbell: Autograph letter signed to Bastian concerning heterogenesis. 1 page, 1904 Apr. 26 (Box 1)
  - Gore, George: Autograph letter signed to Bastian concerning bacterial heterogenesis. 1 page, 1904 May 5 (Box 1)
  - Greenstreet, W. J.: Typed letter signed to Bastian, with autograph additions, concerning Studies in Heterogenesis. 3 pp., 1904 May 5 (Box 1)
  - Greenstreet, W. J.: Autograph postcard to Bastian, 1904 May 7 (Box 1)
  - Ruata, Chas.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian re Heterogenetic Origin of Bacteria. 2+ pp., 1904 May 8 (Box 1)
  - Living, Edward: Letter signed to Bastian appointing Bastian Senior Censor for the Royal College of Physicians. 1 page, 1904 July 13 (Box 1)
  - Holmes, Gordon: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, 1904 July 21 (Box 1)
  - Lockyer, J. Norman: Autograph letter signed to Bastian, mentioning Lockyer's Inorganic Evolution. 1 page plus integral blank, 1904 Nov. 2 (Box 1)
  - Saleeby, Caleb Williams: Autograph note signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1904 Dec. 1 (Box 1)
  - Oliver, James: Autograph letter signed to Bastian concerning Bastian's Studies in Heterogenesis. 2 pp., 1904 Dec. 15 (Box 1)
  - Duncan, R. K.: Correspondence with Bastian regarding a proposed book by Bastian dealing with the whole problem of the origin and nature of life. 3 pieces (9 pp. total), 1905 Jan. 12 (Box 1)
  - Stewart, C.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1 page, 1905 Mar. 13 (Box 1)
  - T. Fisher Unwin: Typed letter signed accepting a work by Bastian for publication. 2+ pp., 1905 June 26 (Box 1)
  - T. Fisher Unwin: Typed letter signed negotiating terms of publication. 2+ pp., 1905 June 28 (Box 1)
  - Williams & Norgate: Statement of account for sales of Heterogenesis. 4+ pp., 1905 June 30 (Box 1)
  - Williams & Norgate: Typed letter signed concerning sales of Heterogenesis. 1 page, 1905 Nov. 4 (Box 1)
  - Lunquist(?), Alfred: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2+ pp., 1905 Nov. 8 (Box 1)
  - Fox, Howard: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1905 Nov. 23 (Box 1)
  - Duncan, D.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2+ pp., 1905 Nov. 24 (Box 1)
  - Saleeby, Caleb Williams: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1 page, 1905 Dec. 6 (Box 1)
  - Methuen & Co: Correspondence concerning a contract for proposed book by Bastian. 4 pieces, 1905 Dec. 12 (Box 1)
  - Ker, William Paton: Group of 4 autograph letters signed to Mrs. Bastian. (Box 2)
    Ker was Professor of English at University College, London and later professor of poetry at Oxford.
  - Ker, William Paton: Group of 13 autograph letters signed to Sybil Bastian, 1905-1919 (Box 2)
  - Ker, William Paton: Group of 11 autograph letters signed to Sybil Bastian, 1906-1920 (Box 2)
  - Pavy, F. W.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 1 page, 1906 Jan. 29 (Box 2)
  - Overington, Stephen.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian concerning abiogenesis. 3 pp., 1906 Feb. 12 (Box 2)
  - Fisher, W. E. Garrett: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1906 Feb. 23 (Box 2)
  - Broadbent, W. F.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 3 pp., 1906 Mar. 4 (Box 2)
  - Broadbent, W. F.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 3 pp., 1906 Mar. 7 (Box 2)
  - Broadbent, W. F.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 3 pp., 1906 Mar. 13 (Box 2)
  - Harris, Wilfrid: Autograph note signed. 1 page, 1906 Mar. 16 (Box 2)
  - Gore, G.: Autograph letter signed to Bastian on origin of life question. 2 pp., 1906 Mar. 26 (Box 2)
  - Burke, J. Butler: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 3 pp., 1906 Apr. 9 (Box 2)
  - Harris, Wilfrid: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 2 pp., 1906 Dec. 2 (Box 2)
  - Methuen & Co.: Typed letter signed to Bastian, with Bastian's note at the foot. 1 page, 1906 Dec. 19 (Box 2)
  - Methuen & Co: Typed letter signed to Bastian. 1 sheet, 1907 Feb. 9 (Box 2)
  - Bell, W. Blau: Autograph letter signed to Bastian concerning The Evolution of Life. 2 pp., 1907 Feb. 14 (Box 2)
  - Marie, Pierre: Autograph letter signed to Bastian. 3 pp., 1907 Feb. 12 (Box 2)